A Guide to the Martha Hill Newell Papers, 1933-2007
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Martha Hill Newell Papers, 1933-2007
The Library of Virginia
43570
3.05 cu. ft. (7 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dawn A. Westbrook-Boyd, Mechanicsville, 2007 December.
Biographical Information
Martha Hill Newell was born 26 July 1921 to Marshall Nelson Newell and Jessie Beatrice Hill in Richmond, Virginia. She received her undergraduate degree from William and Mary and master's degree from Richmond Polytechnic Institute. She was a drama consultant to the special education division of Richmond Public Schools and wrote plays for Richmond Children's Theatre. In 1955 she moved to New York where she worked for The Girl Scouts of America as their events chairwoman and as a book editor and writer for publishing firms. She was a member of The Dramatists Guild and very active in the theatre. In 1995 she returned to Richmond to continue writing, producing, and directing her own plays. She wrote more than twenty plays, including The Day Joe Montana Retired, Dogs and Other Actors, Endings, Phillis Wheatley, and Wives, Babies, and VMI. A resident of Westminster Canterbury in Richmond, she passed away 6 June 2007.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1933-2007, of Martha Hill Newell of Richmond, Virginia, and New York. The bulk of the collection consists of plays written by Newell, including stage notes, revisions, flyers, and programs. The collection also includes clippings, correspondence, teaching notes, and a yearbook from the 1933 class of Patrick Henry School in Richmond.
Contents List
- Awards, 1953. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1938-2002 (bulk 2000-2002). (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1974-2003 (bulk 2002-2003). (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Liberty Lovers Annual yearbook, Patrick Henry School, 1933 Feb.. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Flyers and programs, Angel from Hell, 1949-1950. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Flyers and programs, The Day Joe Montana Retired, 1999-2005. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Flyers and programs, Dogs and Other Actors, 2003-2004. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Flyers and programs, The Elephant's Graveyard, 2000-2004. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Flyers and programs, Endings, 2001. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Flyers and programs, Names, ca. 2000. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Flyers and programs, Phillis Wheatley, 1981-2007. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Flyers and programs, Two By One, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Flyers and programs, Wives, Babies, and VMI, 2007. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Flyers and programs, Theatres, Barksdale Theatre, 2006. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Flyers and programs, Theatres, Firehouse Theatre, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Flyers and programs, Theatres, Green Mountain Playhouse, ca. 1960. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Flyers and programs, Theatres, Rice Playhouse, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Flyers and programs, Theatres, Virginia High School League, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Flyers and programs, Misc. ca. 2000-2005. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Notes, Acting. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Notes, Actor-Director Workshop. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Notes, Playwriting class. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Notes, Misc. (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
- Notes, Teaching. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Notes, Westminster-Canterbury. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Notes, Workshop. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Production notes and research, Dogs and Other Actors. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Production notes and research, Endings. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Production notes and research, Phillis Wheatley. (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Production notes and research, Miscellaneous. (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
- Resume. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Resume, Scrapbook. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Framed program notes, Manhattan Punch Line presents The Comedy Corps in Friends, Lovers, (And Others Beyond The Fringe). (Box 2, Folder 10)
- A list of plays. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Plays, The Adventure of Herbert, A Story for Very Young People. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Plays, Alwasia and the Witch. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Plays, Angel from Hell. (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
- Plays, Bosoms and Rhett Butler. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Plays, A Cup of Clay. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Plays, The Day Joe Montana Retired. (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
- Plays, Dogs and Other Actors. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Plays, The Elephant's Graveyard. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Plays, The Elephant's Graveyard. (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Plays, Endings. (Box 4, Folder 4-9)
- Plays, The English Lessons. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Plays, Follies. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Plays, The Free and the Brave. (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- Plays, The Frog Prince and Alwasia and the Witch. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Plays, The Gift of Belief. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Plays, Mr. Monkey and the Magic Cobra. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Plays, Names. (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
- Plays, Names, Photographs. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Plays, Our Town or The Booster Club is Doing Our Town But I'm Too Old To Play Emily. (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
- Plays, Phillis, A Story of Phillis Wheatley, 1761-1784. (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
- Plays, Phillis, A Story of Phillis Wheatley, 1761-1784. (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
- Plays, Phillis, A Story of Phillis Wheatley, 1761-1784. (Box 7)
- Plays, Rumplestiltskin. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Plays, Sweet Revenge. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Plays, Two short plays (or revue sketches), Untitled, and Fish Gotta Swim Birds Gotta Fly. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Plays, Wives, Babies, and VMI. (Box 6, Folder 7-11)